Guide to the Duff Green Papers, 1818-1909 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duff Green papers 1818-1909 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Green, Duff, d. ca. 1854.
1.6 linear feet Extent: 1,855 Items
Merchant and manufacturer of Falmouth, Virginia. Correspondence, ledgers, daybooks, account books, and other business records (chiefly 1822-1875) of Green and his various associates, illustrating activities such as retailing, grain milling and merchandising, and cotton cloth manufacturing. The bulk of the collection is in the form of bound manuscript volumes. Firms represented include the Bellmont and Eagle flour mills, the Falmouth Manufacturing Company, and the Elm Cotton Factory. The papers also reflect the emergence of Fredericksburg, Va., as a business center, and the decline of Falmouth.
RL.00479
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Duff Green Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1972, 1973, and 1975.
Biographical Note
Duff Green (d. ca. 1854) was a merchant and manufacturer of Falmouth, Virginia.
Collection Overview
Collection includes business records of Duff Green (d. ca. 1854), merchant and manufacturer, of his son, McDuff, and of their partners and successors in a business dealing in various types of produce, including wheat, flour, textile products, general merchandise, etc. The firm operated under various names, including Duff Green, Duff Green and Son, the son apparently being William J. Green (d. ca. 1871), Green and Lane, and Green and Scott.
Unbound papers consist principally of business and a few personal letters. Bound volumes comprise records of the Bellemont and Eagle flour mills and other flour mills, and relate to the inspection of flour; cotton factories, generally branches of the Falmouth Manufacturing Company, owned and operated by the Greens, Scotts, and Lanes; a large general mercantile establishment, and dividends accruing to the various partners. There are full accounts of the operation of the Elm Cotton Factory, where Osnaburg, sail duck, bagging, wagon tents, etc. were manufactured as early as 1842. Mercantile ledgers and daybooks show the sale of various types of farm supplies, such as Osnaburg, ground plaster, flour, clover seed, and sundries. Unbound volumes include daybooks; ledgers; account books; records of cotton purchased, wood hauled, cloth shipped, flour sent by boat, and wheat hauled; cashbooks; memoranda; baling books; wool-carding books; time books; records of production, cash sales, wages, and expenses; letter books; invoices; notes and bills; and receiving and delivery books.
The records equally concern flour milling, general merchandise, and textile manufacture. There are also volumes of George J. Lightner and of John M. O'Bannon, who apparently had business connections with Duff Green. The records reflect the gradual emergence of Fredericksburg as a business center and the consequent decline of Falmouth.
Subject Headings
Elm Cotton Factory (Falmouth, Va.); Falmouth Manufacturing Company (Falmouth, Va.); Business records; Cotton textile industry -- Virginia; Flour mills -- Virginia; Merchants -- Virginia -- Falmouth; Industries -- Virginia; Falmouth (Va.) -- Commerce; Fredericksburg (Va.) -- Commerce
Contents of Collection
- Duff Green Papers, 1818-1909 and undated, (4 boxes)
  Collection includes correspondence, ledgers, daybooks, account books, and other business records. There are many dozens of bound manuscript volumes, chiefly business records, housed separately.
  - Correspondence, 1825-1845 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1846-1909 and undated (Box 2)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1818-1859 (Box 3)
  - Bills and Receipts, 1860-1879 and undated (Box 4)
  - Bound Manuscript volumes
    Bound manuscript volumes include ledgers, daybooks, account books, and other business records.
    - Bound manuscript volumes, oversize (Box 5)
    - Bound manuscript volumes, oversize (Box 6)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1079)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1127)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1130)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1132)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1146)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1147)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1148)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1149)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1150)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1151)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1152)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1153)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1155)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1156)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1161)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1163)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1166)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1168)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1169)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1170)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1172)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1173)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1176)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1177)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1178)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1181)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1183)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1184)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1185)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1186)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1197)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1198)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1199)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1202)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1203)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1206)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1207)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1208)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1209)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1232)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1586)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1587)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1588)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1589)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:1595)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:2285)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:2286)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:2287)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:2289)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:2291)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:2390)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:2393)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:4237)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:4238)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume F:4239)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1101)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1102)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1103)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1128)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1129)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1131)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1133)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1135)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1141)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1145)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1154)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1157)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1158)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1159)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1160)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1162)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1167)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1175)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1179)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1180)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1182)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1187)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1188)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1190)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1191)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1192)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1193)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1194)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1195)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1200)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1201)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1204)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1210)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1211)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1212)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1215)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1216)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1220)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1226)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1227)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1228)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1229)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1230)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1231)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1234)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1236)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1237)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1242)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1582)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1584)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1590)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1591)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1592)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1593)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1596)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:1597)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:2288)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:2290)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:2391)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:2392)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:2394)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:2395)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:4240)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume L:4241)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1134)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1136)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1137)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1139)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1140)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1142)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1213)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1214)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1217)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1218)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1221)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1223)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1224)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1233)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1239)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1240)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1241)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1580)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1583)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1585)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume M:1594)
    - Bound manuscript volume (Box 6, Volume S:1406)